hi this week we're going to talk about
how to break a fast how to make it easy
and some of the dangers you have to look
out for and what the refeeding syndrome
is who's at risk and why you need to
know about it and it's coming right
[Music]
up when you haven't eaten for a while
your body starts to slow down its
digestive process so the enzymes the
pancreatic enzymes the stomach acids and
all those sort of things are going to
slow down because they simply don't need
it so much so if you are to eat a lot of
food in a very short period of time
right after fasting sometimes there's a
bit of a uh lag so you start to get some
symptoms and we've all made this mistake
before where you eat too much after a
fast and you start to feel the bloating
or you start to feel the nausea some
people get diarrhea and some people get
a bad stomach ache that's very very
common and that's just that mismatch
between how much you've eaten and how
quickly your body is able to digest it's
probably uh due to the fact that uh your
physical hunger is not that high whereas
your psychological hunger probably is
much higher that is you haven't eaten
for a while so you see something that's
just delicious so then you're like oh I
need to eat a lot because I haven't
eaten for a while so then you've eaten a
lot more than your body can physically
handle and it's usually not a problem
most of the time after the first uh
couple of times it happens most people
are able to figure out that there's this
mismatch and are able to
adjust also if your fast is less than 24
hours it doesn't tend to be a big issue
because uh your body isn't so far out of
practice but you do see it once you
start to go over that period of time so
there are a few foods that we've noticed
which tend to be a little bit more
problematic than others and it varies by
the person but there are a few general
rules so nuts and seeds nut Butters eggs
dairy wine and fibrous vegetables they
all tend to have a little bit of
problems and I think it's probably
because these are foods that maybe are
not quite as easy to digest it takes a
little bit more uh of the stomach acid
and the uh enzymes to break them down so
nuts and seeds can be a little bit of a
problem things like um wine and uh eggs
and da they're more individual some
people tolerate them no problem so here
are some tips plan a pre-meal to sort of
wake up the digestion 30 minutes prior
to your main meal so for example if you
decide okay I'm need to lose a little
bit of weight and I'm going to fast and
then you fast for 24 hours 36 hours then
instead of jumping right into dinner or
jumping right into lunch or whatever
meal that you're planning to break your
fast with what you want to do is say
okay well I know that it's dinner is
coming up I'm going to plan something
small 30 minutes prior and it's just
going to be limited in quantity so that
you're not tempted to overeat it but at
the same time it's just going to
gradually sort of wake that up and this
might be a little small portion of say
fish or beef or something that's um
cooked vegetables
avocado um the only thing you want to
avoid is uh raw vegetables because the
cooking usually makes the uh vegetable
much easier to digest and therefore it's
it's going to go down a lot easier and
it's just going to be a small portion so
that you're not tempted to overeat the
foods um because you know there's only a
little bit at the same time you know
that in half an hour you're going to get
the full meal so that psychologically
you're prepared for that and that's just
a little bit of something you can also
take some some say water with Chia seed
it's got a little bit of fiber just to
start getting the process going so that
your body is able to go and digest the
meal
regularly where you really want to be
careful is when you're fasting for
multiple days and generally over 5 to 10
days of fasting then you have to be
aware of something called the refeeding
syndrome and this is something that we
used to see in the 40s and 50s when
we're dealing with a lot of people uh
after the war where there's a lot of
people who hadn't eaten properly for
months or even years sometimes and what
happens during the refeeding syndrome is
that the body is
really wants to build up its proteins
and its cells after having not eaten for
a long period of time so when you start
to eat all of these the proteins and the
minerals and everything starts to go
into the cells in order to start to
rebuild some of these cells but the
problem is that when it all goes from
the blood into the cells to try and uh
increase the the production of these new
cells the levels in the blood actually
drops very very low so what you get is a
severe depletion in the blood levels of
pottassium magnesium phosphorus and
thamin predominantly and when it all
goes into the cells to make new cells
the blood levels fall so low that they
can actually cause a lot of symptoms and
in severe cases it can even cause heart
rhythm disturbances and people had
actually died from this and that's why
it's so so
important the key hormone in this is
insulin because as we start to eat
insulin starts to go up and that's a
signal for all of these vitamins and
minerals uh to come from the blood and
go into the cells and because there's a
lot more volume in the cells than there
is in the blood it only takes a little
bit of that potassium and magnesium and
phosphorus to come out of the blood for
the blood levels to fall so low that you
can run into problems and that's called
the refeeding
syndrome there are certain groups of
people that are at very high risk of
developing refeeding syndrome and those
are people who have not been getting
adate nutrition for a fairly lengthy
period of time so when you look at
people with the eating disorder anorexia
nervosa uh chronic alcoholism these
people haven't eaten properly for a long
time cancer patient who are very
catabolic and they're breaking down a
lot of their tissues people after
surgery who haven't eaten properly due
to those physical restraints that stop
them from eating or elderly patients
with other uh problems such as dementia
where they don't uh feel like eating and
they haven't eaten for a long period of
time those are the people that you
really have to look out for they really
shouldn't be fasting obviously because
the for those people nutrition is very
important and we don't want to be
depriving them of nutrients the other
thing that you should be aware of is
certain medications so if you're using
ant acids for a long time the magnesium
and the aluminum uh in those antacids
can bind phosphorus and remember
phosphorus in the blood is one of those
key minerals that gets decreased so low
that can it can actually cause heart
failure and heart weakness the other uh
group of uh medications is diuretics and
those are often used for high blood
pressure and diuretics uh make you pee
more but it tends to deplete the body of
electrolytes and in this case the
magnesium and the potassium are the key
electrolytes here that get wasted in the
urine when you're taking these diuretics
and when you get the refeeding syndrome
uh it can go even lower so be careful in
those groups of patients or if you're
taking those medications so when you're
trying to break a fast on a regular
basis remember you can take it slow the
longer you're fast the slower you should
go you can plan a pre-meal um to avoid
uh eating too much and getting your body
woken up to the system but the other
problem we see a lot is that people tend
to take things that are a little bit too
sweet and the sweetness uh even if it
has no calories will tend to stimulate
the appetite so again what you're trying
to do is break that fast slower than
usual and think taking things like
artificial sweeteners well that's going
to just make you more hungry it's going
to increase that sort of
psychological uh need for the food and
therefore you're going to tend to
overeat so do try to avoid while you're
fasting or towards the end to avoid
those sort of um sugar substitutes or
non-caloric uh
sweeteners just remember that there's a
difference between the psychological
hunger and the physical hunger the
physical hunger tends to be a lot less
people don't actually feel so much of it
but the need to eat something tends to
be very high so it's by avoiding these
sort of traps that you can break your
fast properly and make sure that you're
doing it in a healthy way and if you
want to learn more about fat fasting
what you can do is check out this video
that I did on the five stages of
intermittent fasting and what we do is
we go over what happens in the body as
you're going through the stages of
fasting it can really help you on your
journey I'll see you next week